with patience the most Tangled cord may
be undone I'm Ry Myers I'm currently
Chief Architect at all hands AI which
makes a coding agent called open hands
but we have um a Meetup in town on
Monday if you'd like to hear about that
I'd like to talk about something
different
today and you can go to this QR code and
find the slides and some other materials
you might like to play with if you like
I'll show that again at the
end now I study Legacy code and ways of
working with it in order to know that
those Ways work I test them on the most
extreme examples I can find some of the
worst code I can find so let's look at
today's Tangled
chord
beautiful utterly incomprehensible I
love stuff like this now this is by a
fellow named Andy Sloan and it was a
winner of the 2006 International OB
fiscated C code contest the ioc CCC
there are contests apparently for making
unreadable code and I have a lot of fun
with their winners so what does that do
right obviously we cannot tell by
looking at it what it does so um let's
run
it so we compile it we run it it's got
this askart there's like this spinning
3D donut in the middle you might be able
to see better than the other monitors
there's a a checker board waving back
and forth it'll come around again
there's a banner at the top that says
ioccc 2006 the name of the
contest just that blob of code does all
of that how does it work how could this
possibly work and more importantly for
us how could we know what if you went to
work on Monday and the code in the
repository looked like this and you had
to maintain it and if you didn't the
payment system would break or something
right like what we do the tools that
would help us even in this situation
those are tools I trust that's the
exercise we're doing here now as I
happen to be playing with that one it
was March 2023 you may remember that
month well gp4 was released we had seen
chat TPT before that but when gp4 came
out things got a little weird it was
much more Lucid than we we had seen
before and the Cod examples were very
impressive we started wondering any
little thing we're doing can chat GPT
just do this for me and so we can paste
all that into chat gbt it's small enough
to fit in a prompt hey Chad gbt can you
improve this code and it will report
that yes certainly I
can certainly I
can here's an improved version of the
code blah blah blah and this is the
result now you could paste that and
compile it you may know what's going to
happen here not only is this not an
improved version of the code I gave it
it's not even code it doesn't compile it
is a codel likee substance that has come
out of this but to give it credit there
are some insights being expressed in
terms of things we might like to do with
the code that are reasonable we would
just need to execute them in some other
way now when you point out the
limitations of a particular technology
as you should do with all technology in
this space for some reason people have
this refrain they uh they say the models
will get better you may have heard it so
real quick I'm going to recap the last
two years of the models getting better
since some time has passed now gp4
breaks the code Claude Opus breaks the
code GPT 40 breaks the code Claude 3.5
Sonet breaks the code now the models
were getting better that is true 3.5
Sonet is amazing I don't want to
downplay that
but um in on not only pathological
examples like this but even moderately
challenging Legacy code it will break it
if you let it edit it so then we thought
maybe we need reasoning models so they
won't make such obvious errors so now 01
could now break the code and finally a
few weeks ago you may have heard Deep
seek R1 came out with a breakthrough in
reinforcement learning in the training
process that was so shocking that it
caused a$1 trillion correction in the
stock exchange and I am now able to
report that finally it also breaks the
code so I know you may have some code
that it doesn't break that's fine or you
may have some code you don't mind if it
breaks and that's fine but for some of
us our reality is that the new magic
breaks our code
what if we were to just accept that what
does that
mean well we will need the old magic as
well we will maybe need them both
together so what is the old magic well
one thing we do in the old magic is we
have tests so let's put some tests
around this code and it's actually
relatively easy to test all it does is
spit out a bunch of output so we could
capture that to a file take the first
5,000 lines of output from this file and
that happens to be more the full cycle
of the rotation if we modify the code
run it again and get an identical log
file out of it we can be pretty Convent
we haven't broken
anything excellent so we have our safety
net let's look at this code a little
closer so to get this running well in a
modern system I did a couple things out
the
gate so I added the argument types to
the main function and others that had
been inferred for instance in C the
arguments to main are always in tinar
star
star and I added that little you can see
it on the monitors a sleep function at
the very end in an outer loop I had
found which adds enough DeLay So the
animation plays on Modern computers and
you were able to see
it
now the test pass real quickly I'm going
to point out actually also that at the
top
I can go
back there's a um there's a notation at
the top here that has an at sign before
the uh commit message and that at sign
indicates that I edited the code with my
hands that's significant here because
the last time I'm going to do that
because my dirty little hands are too
unsafe for me to be editing this code
that's the level of paranoia we're
exercising here we are going to avoid
manual edits so um our next edit
fortunately is automated and it is to
run the formatter you may normally trust
the formatter which is fine on code this
treacherous sometimes the formatter
breaks it formatters are not perfect so
in order to make sure the uh formatter
has done its job I'm going to compile it
run the formatter compile it again and
diff the binaries themselves and they
are identical so I believe that I can
save this format
code so this is what it looks like
now it doesn't look like code I can
understand but it does at least look
like code and not ask Art this is
progress so let's look at the first
function here I'm going to ask chat GPT
for help again I'm still having trouble
reading it but I'm GNA ask it
differently now I'm going to ask it
instead of giving me the new code give
me some things you would like to do to
this I will figure figure out how to get
them done right um and it suggests
renaming this from P to render glyph
might be a good idea I'm not really sure
at this point it makes several other
suggestions so I'm going to implement
them again not with my hands but with
the safest tool I I know right now as I
was doing this uh the jet brains IDE to
do safe renames and other refactoring
operations so we'll carry out the rename
that way and the test passed because
when you do automated syntax transforms
they almost always pass tests are almost
redund at that point um applying several
others and adding Loop braces using the
linter this time um use the ID to
convert a tary to an if Etc not going to
go run through every single change but
it's all in the repo if you want to look
um it's renamed this is a helpful change
actually very helpful renaming B to
frame buffer which is is global here
that's going to help a lot in
understanding all the rest of the code
everywhere that's used because the the
that frame bar offer is where the
characters are assigned before they are
displayed to the screen so this is what
we're ultimately producing to to make
that
animation uh then we extract a constant
which indicates the width of the
terminal several other
constants um The Prompt I was using at
the time I later developed into a GPT on
the GPT store which used to be a thing
remember uh called refactor GPT but I
think this audience is probably somewhat
experienced at M prompting so um you can
look it up in the slides if you like but
I'm not going to cover that in depth
right now the point is I'm asking it not
for new code but saying specifically
don't list new code just give me
suggestions of the kind that I'm able to
execute in a safe tool so this is
basically like llm tool use if you've
done
that um so we have some more suggestions
from chat gbt over on the main method
and I'm going to apply some of them an
example of how we're bootstrapping from
very little insight but just getting
what we can out of it is it's saying
let's make a angle a the reason we could
know that it's angle a is because it's
being passed to S and cosine and the
only thing you can pass to those is is
angles the only thing that makes any
sense so I'll take it I may not know
what A and B are but they are
angles all right it's also suggested and
I took at the time a suggestion of
renaming the function e to render donut
now that turns out to be a mistake you
might call it an llm hallucination or
just a bad suggestion or whatever but um
what's nice here is that it's not a
suggestion that breaks anything I hadn't
really allowed the opportunity for bad
llm output to break anything it's just
going to give me a confusing name for a
while until I realized the problem the
code continue to work um another thing
here is that the initializers are all on
one line because this person codes like
a lunatic on purpose and so using the
the linter I can spread those out into
multiple lines applying several other
suggestions
and moving on so I've noticed like a uh
a blob of stuff
here um with that uh that outer for loop
it's for some reason not highlighting on
the on the big screen but I've noticed a
blob of something that in the in the OU
for Loop that looks like it could be
extracted not entirely sure what it does
it does a lot of calculations and then
it updates the frame buffer so I'm just
going to call it update frame buffer and
we'll figure out more about what it does
later
perhaps so more or less at this point I
realized that what I had called um
render donut before is actually should
be render B
Banner so that gets renamed and this
remaining bit at the top with that for
Loop um must
be up rendering the checker board sort
of by process of elimination and if you
look there's a string if you can see it
in the middle that has a DOT and a pound
sign meaning that's the only two things
that block of code sets in the frame
buffer and if you look at the animation
the checkerboard is the part that only
has dots and hashtags so that must be
render
checkerboard all right now this main
method is actually starting to look
pretty respectable I can kind of see the
phases of operation um the part that is
not obvious to me yet is these control
codes that are being uh printed out so
we could look that up but we chat gbt is
actually perfectly capable of giving us
enough context to know the the first one
should be clear screen and the second
one is move cursor to home so we'll
comments there so here we have the the
final code at Le where I ended up uh
stopping that particular session there's
a bunch of constants at the top some
nasty globals there that if you look at
the data flow is not actually that hard
to to get rid of and make uh make non-
globals then there's
five helper functions that have been
extracted this is render donut which is
uh maybe the most interesting part of
the program
it is doing some very complex
trigonometry to draw this
three-dimensional donut and at the
bottom there's that magic string which
has sort of ascending levels of shading
to paint the dut different different
ways and I realize this is complex code
but within the space of you're drawing a
three-dimensional object and then doing
like primitive Ray tracing on it it is
now fairly
straightforward so it's more doing a
complex thing than fiscated
intentionally at least then we have
render Checker boards doing some much
simpler trigonometry just a sign to make
it waver back and forth and then some
some math to to draw this sort of
projected square and draw draw it with
either a DOT
or hashtag depending on whether it's
like the the white or black parts of the
checkerboard there is render Banner here
which this one actually is still kind of
a mystery at this point like it's got
two helper functions which they'll um
suggested to name code to index and
render glyph which kind of seem like
reasonable names but we don't really
understand in context what's going on
here there's some magic strings and then
these two helper functions so and this
giant magic string here is a total
mystery so call call that one mostly
lost and then after we put whatever we
do in the frame buffer this is print
frame buffer that actually just renders
or frame of the animation and the main
function that drives it so I'm going to
say looking at this not too shabby this
is not now great code it's not now even
clean code but I can work with it now I
I've made multiple changes added
features to it based on this where
before it was just completely
incomprehensible
so not not bad for for one session right
and in that process humans almost never
directly touched the code automation
made most of the changes and LMS never
directly edited code only made
suggestions and nothing broke there was
rarely even a a test failure if there
ever was
one so what what did we use to do this
well it is true to say we used AI that
is something that happened right but a
lot a lot was going on different
components kind of used to their
strength right you have a human expert
in Legacy code you have a language model
gp4 you have algorithms in the form of
the refactoring support of the jet
brains IDE and the the clang linter and
then you have development practices
which we kind of using lightweight
versions of here which are very powerful
in practice like naming as a process by
Arlo belelli test driven development are
actually a stricter version of it called
test commit revert where we would wipe
out a change if the tests ever failed by
Kent Beck and the forms of the tests we
were using were approval testing which
is popularized by Emily bash and lellan
Falco these are all very useful people
to get to know if you have such such
issues in your life with Legacy code so
the main cycle not the only thing that
was done but the main cycle that we
followed here is AI makes a suggestion I
decide if we want to do it I use the ID
to perform a a factor and run tests and
do an incremental commit now that worked
reasonably well just with me
orchestrating that process manually but
it can be heavily streamlined if I if we
were just to totally streamline it and
and make it
a headless Loop then it would look
something like this and this is another
entry to the same contest we have LM
generated suggestions being um created
and applied test run commits on the left
is the giash of of the commits the
result and then you just kind of watch
the code reshape itself in real time now
you probably want to slow it down a bit
from that and give you some feedback of
like which suggestions are we going to
going to take or leave but you know this
this can get very smooth and lest we be
limited to only doing refactoring
operations because even though those do
get very uh powerful there's obviously
things we would want to do other than
that there's also this whole branch of
computer science called formal methods
which I ended up spending most the last
year learning and on my YouTube channel
craft versus CR uh that generated about
12 different videos maybe my next talk
we'll focus more uh heavily on that but
after that year what I was left
wondering is why are we putting so much
on whether or not we're able to get llms
to exhibit reasoning capabilities when
automated theorem provs already
exist um I think they're being almost
entirely left out of the conversation
how many in here have used a proof
assistant
ever awesome awesome that guy's cool and
if you use prologue half a point so
anyway we're going to need a lot of
tricks we'll need a lot of different
tools here because new code is easy it's
easy for AI and it's easy for people new
code was not the hard problem this whole
time old code is hard but here's the
problem new code becomes old
code may have noticed this so just
focusing on what works on new code is
not a long-term strategy it does it does
not work and this won't be easy we
should not expect it to
be some problems an AI is not going to
just come on along and solve for us like
for instance how does that Banner code
work the AI couldn't help us figure that
out
and somehow that magic string becomes
that Banner the answer's got to be in
there somewhere
so anyway um back in March 2023 I posted
that initial session and I actually
ended up inadvertently summoning the
original author Andy Sloan he commented
on it and said many interesting things
including I am amused and somewhat
satisfied that nobody's figured out how
the logo is encoded in 15 years and now
chat GPT can't
either well we couldn't really let that
slide now could we so six hours later
that I will never see again I did figure
out how the banner was done and you
might you know remember some of these uh
terms from computer science class if not
that's fine but there is a runlength
encoding done that produces uh a result
that's encoded with two different
Huffman encodings that is produced a
long binary string which is divided into
six bit chunks and then reversed for no
good reason and those chunks are
converted into a Bas 64 asking en coding
using the characters between greater
than sign and
Tilda and that is how this becomes this
magic
string I'll let the author
know I think this is what you're doing
he confirmed indeed I had figured out
and I was the first person to do so and
I will prove to you now that I do have
the exact encoding process because I can
replace that magic string now with
another magic string we can run into
again and put a different message in
it so instead of
ioccc it now says AI native
death and Patrick that is a great name
but perhaps the better name for this one
would have been Dev native AI thank you
New York